Leo Hurwitz collection, 1910-1992, bulk 1925-1991
George Eastman Museum
- Series 16, Calendars/Address Books, 1935-1991; 1961-1991
  Series includes desk calendars, pocket notebooks, address books, and card files. Some contain notes and business cards.
  - no title (Box C006)
    - [1974 desk and pocket calendars, 1975 desk calendar] (Folder 23a)
      1974 desk calendar starts in June.
    - [1980 daily desk diary] (Folder 23b)
      Bound calendar
    - [Desk calendars for 1985, 1988, and 1989] (Folder 23c)
      Desk calendars for 1985, 1988 [including part of 1987], and 1989 [including part of 1988].
  - no title (Box C061)
    - [Bag labeled: Calendars 1976-1983] (Folder 3)
      Personal engagement calendars, with entries and notes inside.
  - no title (Box C068)
    - [1967 appointment calendar] (Folder 4)
      Calendar with personal entries and notes.
  - no title (Box C075)
    - [Bag labeled: Calendar '87], 1987 (Folder 1)
      Desk calendar from 1987, with entries and notes.
    - [Envelope labeled: 1986 calendar] (Folder 2)
      Desk calendar from 1986, with entries and notes.
  - no title (Box C086)
    - [Envelope labeled: Old address books], undated (Folder 4)
      Six address books.
    - [Autodex], undated (Folder 7)
      Autodex address finder with completed cards inside.
  - no title (Box C092)
    - [1982 German calendar] (Folder 14)
  - no title (Box C094)
    - [Address books -- Hurwitz and Nelly Burlingham], undated (Folder 2)
      Three filled-in address books, two for Hurwitz (one marked "Europe" on the inside cover) and one for Nelly Burlingham. Notes and business cards included inside.
    - [Engagement calendars], 1964-1973; 1986 (Folder 3)
      Hurwitz's engagement calendars for years 1964, 1965, 1967, 1968, 1969, 1973, and 1986, with entries, notes, and business cards.
  - no title (Box C096)
    - [Professional correspondence, Detroit Institute of Arts calendar], 1969-1970 (Folder 7)
  - no title (Box C097)
    - [1978 and 1980 desk calendar pages], ca. 1963 (Folder 4d)
      Desk calendar pages for the years 1978 and 1980, housed in labeled paper bags.
    - [1981 and 1982 desk calendar pages], 1981-1982 (Folder 4e)
      Desk calendar pages for the years 1981 [originally found loose] and 1982 [housed in a labeled envelope].
    - [Rolodex], undated (Folder Box 1)
      Desktop card index containing names, addresses, and telephone numbers.
  - no title (Box C104)
    - [1966 engagement calendar] (Folder 4)
      Calendar, with entries.
  - no title (Box C106)
    - [Bag labeled: 1983 calendar] (Folder 1)
      1983 desk calendar, with entries.
    - [1961 desk diary] (Folder 2)
      1961 personal calendar, with entries.
  - no title (Box C186)
    - [Pocket notebook], ca. 1935 (Folder 4e)
      Contains notes, contact information, and budget.
  - no title (Box C218)
    - [1984 engagement calendar] (Folder 2)
      Spiral-bound calendar with attached notes.
    - [Shoebox labeled: Leo: Address books, passports, engagement calendars, misc. papers], 1955; 1961; 1966; 1972; 1977-1980; undated (Folder Box 1)
- Series 17, Paul Strand, 1936-1990
  Series consists of materials related to the photographer and filmmaker Paul Strand and his widow, Hazel Strand. Materials related to the films Hurwitz and Strand made during their years with Frontier Films include correspondence, notes, internal company communications, project proposals and research, outlines, production documents, programs, flyers, and newspaper and magazine clippings. Later materials are related to exhibitions, retrospectives, and documentaries about Strand and his work, including interviews with Hurwitz, correspondence regarding film prints, and an academic dissertation. Note on arrangement of the materials: Strand’s correspondence is not collated together into any one location but is scattered throughout the collection in different folders.
  - no title (Box C003)
    - [Envelope labeled: Tapes & correspondence re: Strand book (and film?) -- Rosenblum], 1990 (Folder 7)
      Correspondence from Walter Rosenblum regarding a book on Paul Strand. Audio tapes have been relocated. Please contact archivist for access.
  - no title (Box C005)
    - Native Land copy #2 -- for script, 1939; 1941; 1945 (Folder 4a)
  - no title (Box C006)
    - [Correspondence], 1970-1971 (Folder 5)
      Correspondents include Paul Strand.
    - [Envelopes containing John B. Rohrbach correspondence and articles], 1990 (Folder 10)
      Contains an abstract and prospectus of John B. Rohrbach's dissertation “Paul Strand: American Photographer"; a draft of his article “Time in New England: Creating a Useable Past”; a photocopy copy of his article “Visions of an Engaged Artist"; and related correspondence.
    - Misc. Correspondence, 1950s-1960s, 1968-1976 (Folder 11)
      Personal, professional, and financial correspondence, including letters from Paul Strand.
    - [Correspondence], 1969-1973 (Folder 13)
      Correspondence includes letters from Sidney Meyers' widow Edna Meyers, with a copy of a letter to Paul Strand.
    - [Correspondence], 1931; 1966-1968 [bulk] (Folder 15)
  - no title (Box C008)
    - [Montage and Modern Life: 1919-1942], 1992 (Folder 20)
      Catalogue from an exhibition mounted by the Institute of Contemporary Art, Boston, with cover letter from curator Matthew Teitelbaum to Nelly Burlingham. Catalog contains a reproduction of a detail from a mural designed by Hurwitz and Paul Strand.
  - no title (Box C011)
    - Misc. -- Strand (FF), 1962-1965; undated (Folder 9b)
      Material concerning a monograph on the work of Paul Strand, including correspondence from Strand.
  - no title (Box C024)
    - [Shoebox labeled: Strand letters], 1942-1943; 1951-1964 (Folder Box 2)
      Correspondents include Paul Strand and Hazel Strand.
  - no title (Box C026)
    - [Correspondence, clippings, and receipts], 1965-1968 (Folder 1b)
      Personal correspondence includes letters from Paul Strand.
  - no title (Box C029)
    - [Shoebox labeled: Letters 1940s], 1941-1955 (Folder Box 1)
      Includes correspondence from Paul Strand.
  - no title (Box C039)
    - [Bag labeled: Bank statements and insurance policies, etc.], 1975-1980 (Folder 1)
      Personal correspondence, including a letter from Hazel Strand regarding the rights to Paul Strand's work.
  - no title (Box C040)
    - [Correspondence], 1957-1962 (Folder 1)
      Personal correspondence from family members and friends, including Paul Strand. Subjects include a series of films on Strand.
    - Eichmann -- to file, 1956; 1960-1965 (Folder 3)
      Includes correspondence from Paul Strand (which includes a letter to George Eastman House director Beaumont Newhall requesting a 'lavender' or interpositive of Native Land.
    - Correspondence -- miscellaneous, 1958-1969 (Folder 18)
      Includes correspondence with Paul Strand.
    - File -- desk stuff -- approx. 1959, 1957-1962 (Folder 19)
      Personal and professional correspondence, including letters from Paul Strand.
  - no title (Box C043)
    - Current to-do:N.L., "S.L.",H.A.T.W.E.,M&F, misc., people to invite, 1962-1963 (Folder 3f)
  - no title (Box C062)
    - Walker, John, 1986-1988 (Folder 23)
      Correspondence between Hurwitz and John Walker regarding Walker's film Paul Strand--Under the Dark Cloth.
  - no title (Box C073)
    - Correspondence (General), 1944-1958 (Folder 1)
      Includes a letter from Paul Strand mentioning the duplicate negative of Redes/The Wave conserved at George Eastman House, "so at least the film won't be lost"; letters between Hurwitz, Catherine Duncan, Strand, and Henri Langlois regarding Langlois' request for paper material on "Strand's films" for a 60th anniversary of cinema; and correspondence with Strand and Michelle about submitting The Museum and the Fury at the Cannes Film Festival.
    - Correspondence (Native Land-- 1950), 1942; 1945; 1949-1950; 1957 (Folder 16)
  - no title (Box C088)
    - Correspondence 1985-86, current, 1984-1986 (Folder 34)
      Includes correspondence with Naomi Rosenblum regarding the Paul Strand Archive.
  - no title (Box C094)
    - [General -- Paul Strand exhibit, NYU Draft, Sophia Delza article, film catalog], 1970-1972; 1983-1984; ca. 1990 (Folder 7)
      Includes a "Films by Paul Strand" handout from an exhibition and film program sponsored by Southwestern Bell Foundation.
  - no title (Box C102)
    - Hollywood towards job, 1942-1944 (Folder 13)
      Correspondence regarding Hurwitz's efforts to find work in Hollywood. Correspondents include Paul Strand.
  - no title (Box C103)
    - [Envelope labeled: Evaluation -- mail 1975 to be combed], 1975-1976 (Folder 9)
      Cards, memos, invitations, and other personal correspondence, most addressed to Hurwitz at Kirkland College. Correspondents include Hazel Strand and Paul Strand [photocopy].
    - [Envelope labeled: L.H. mail to deal with on Calif. trip], 1976 (Folder 10)
      Includes an invitation to the Paul Strand memorial service, with a draft of Hurwitz's response to Hazel Strand.
  - no title (Box C106)
    - Walker, John, 1988-1989 (Folder 17)
      Correspondence with John Walker of John Walker Productions, Inc., regarding his film Strand:Under the Dark Cloth. Includes photocopies of Walker's letter to the John Allen Lab and arrangements with the Museum of Modern Art regarding the availability of Native Land and Heart of Spain.
  - no title (Box C172)
    - Speeches (come) and notes, 1949-1954 (Folder 9)
      Includes notes by Paul Strand on photography.
  - no title (Box C186)
    - [Folder labeled: Film and scrapbook stuff], 1936-1938; undated (Folder 4f)
      Includes a WQXR radio transcript of a broadcast by Paul Strand regarding Frontier Films, and a program for the premiere of Strand's Redes/The Wave.
  - no title (Box C190)
    - Letters to Leo, 1942-1943; 1951; 1963 (Folder 14)
  - no title (Box C192)
    - [Folder labeled: Misc. stuff of the thirties], 1931-1937 (Folder 2d.2)
      Includes notes on Paul Strand's work and copy of the article "A Portfolio of Mexican Photographs by Paul Strand."
    - [Folder labeled: Farm film], 1936; 1942 (Folder 3f)
      Includes Native Land flyers and comments on the film by New York Trade Union members, and a letter from Paul Strand from Florida.
  - no title (Box C226)
    - [Envelope labeled: Maddow on Strand], 1990 (Folder 11)
  - no title (Box C232)
    - Correspondence 1984, 1983-1984 (Folder 17)
      Includes correspondence regarding a film about Paul Strand.
    - General correspondence -- references, foundation, including researchers, 1974-1979; 1985 (Folder 26)
      Subjects include research on Paul Strand.
- Photographs, 1926-1992
  Series consists primarily of photographs used in the production of films such as Strange Victory,Essay on Death,In Search of Hart Crane,The Sun and Richard Lippold,Dialogue with a Woman Departed,The Museum and the Fury, and the Eichmann trial (including publicity stills for some). Some photographs may have been used for research purposes. Includes photographs of civil rights protests, the Ku Klux Klan, the Kennedy assassination and funeral, artwork, Hart Crane, and childhood photographs of Peggy Lawson. Also includes a small number of portraits of Hurwitz and production shots of him at work. There are very few personal photographs (these are presumed to have been kept by Hurwitz’s family), but some are present, including ones of Tom Hurwitz, Edwin Rolfe, Jane Dudley, and others that are unidentified.
  - no title (Box C003)
    - 89 -- Correspondence: Europe/family/etc., 1986-1991 (Folder 2)
      Includes photographs related to the Leningrad Film Festival.
  - no title (Box C005)
    - Ed R.’s Letters -- 40s to early 50s, 1943-1951 (Folder 3)
  - no title (Box C006)
    - [Envelope labeled: 14 UPI Photos of Civil Rights Struggle of 1960s], 1953-1963 (Folder 16)
      Black-and-white United Press International photographs taken during the Civil Rights Movement. Some captioned on reverse.
  - no title (Box C007)
    - Letters Jerusalem, 1961; 1967 (Folder Box 1)
      Box includes photographs.
  - no title (Box C009)
    - London ’82 -- National Film Theatre retrospective, 1982 (Folder 8)
      Includes a signed photograph of Jane Dudley.
  - no title (Box C012)
    - [Envelope labeled: Photographs], undated (Folder 1)
      Landscape photographs from the Israel Office of Information (New York).
    - [Slide box labeled: Red Rock], 1958 (Folder 3)
      Small box of photographic slides of landscapes from Red Rock [most likely Red Rock Canyon].
  - no title (Box C019)
    - [Box labeled: Duplicates], 1964-1968 (Folder Folder 1)
  - no title (Box C021)
    - [Folder labeled: From P's album], ca. 1945 (Folder 22)
    - [Folder labeled: Peggy photos from Ann (most used in D.W.A.W.D.)], ca. 1930; ca. 1940; 1947; ca. 1950; ca. 1960; 1972 (Folder 23)
    - Jim Jarmusch photos of Leo, ca. 1983 (Folder 23a)
      Photocopies of photographs of Hurwitz with Jim Jarmusch, with a Stranger than Paradise press release.
  - no title (Box C030)
    - Hart Crane photographs/C.U., ca. 1965 (Folder 16)
    - Marsden Hartley --Eight Bells' Folly, 1966 (Folder 17)
    - Essay on Death-- publicity, 1964 (Folder 48)
    - Lippold -- publicity, 1966 (Folder 49)
  - no title (Box C038)
    - [Envelope labeled: A Xmas file], 1967; 1970-1972; undated (Folder 19)
      Includes a 10/21/1967 photo of Tom Hurwitz at the March on the Pentagon with Abbie Hoffman, Peter Gessner, and Susan Steinberg, and undated photos of a black Scottish Terrier (Tammy?).
  - no title (Box C039)
    - [Bag labeled: Bank statements and insurance policies, etc.], 1975-1980 (Folder 1)
      Includes postcards and slides from the Acropolis Museum, Athens.
  - no title (Box C040)
    - Film facilities -- also "general" -- misc. letters, 1956-1961 (Folder 21)
      Includes an American Theatre Wing Professional Training Program Catalog, with an envelope containing a copy of Hurwitz's birth certificate and headshots.
  - no title (Box C043)
    - [Unlabeled envelope containing photo of Leo Hurwitz], undated (Folder 3c)
      8" x 10" black-and-white photograph of Hurwitz on the telephone.
    - [Native Land stills], undated (Folder 3d)
    - [Folder labeled: Eichmann trial -- publicity material & credits], 1961 (Folder 7b)
      Three press photos of Hurwitz, Milton Fruchtman, and crew in the Eichmann trial production control room.
  - no title (Box C055)
    - [Envelope labeled: Return to file --M&F material], undated (Folder 17)
  - no title (Box C071)
    - [Envelope labeled: AL prints], 1963 (Folder 1)
    - [Envelope labeled:Strange Victory stills (II)], ca. 1963 (Folder 2)
    - [Envelope labeled:Strange Victory 23], ca. 1963 (Folder 3)
    - [Envelope labeled: Rejects and extras], ca. 1964 (Folder 4)
    - [Box Labeled:Strange Victory stills for epilogue (I)], ca. 1963 (Folder Folder 1)
  - no title (Box C075)
    - Re: London contacts, ca. 1962; undated (Folder 4)
      Includes publicity photographs from a production of Romeo and Juliet at the Old Vic Company, staring Joanna Dunham and John Stride.
  - no title (Box C089)
    - Helsinki seminars etc. 3/31-4/9/89, 1988-1989 (Folder 49)
      Materials related to Hurwitz's 1989 participation in the Documentary Project of the Finnish Film Foundation, including black-and-white photographs featuring Hurwitz. In Finnish and English.
  - no title (Box C090)
    - [Childhood photographs of Tom Hurwitz], ca. 1955 (Folder 1)
    - [Bag Labeled: Misc. incl: Portugal trip '82, Eleuthera '84, mail], 1980-1984 (Folder 7)
      Materials related to Hurwitz's trips to Portugal and the Bahamas, including color photographs. In English and Portuguese.
  - no title (Box C096)
    - [Correspondence, photograph negative], 1963-1964 (Folder 1)
      Includes a photographic negative sent by Charles Pratt.
    - [Envelope labeled: Kennedy photos -- seq.], 1963 (Folder 8)
    - [Envelope labeled: Extra Polaroids], undated (Folder 9)
      Black-and-white Polaroids of artwork, in a National Educational Television envelope.
    - [Envelope labeled: Publicity pix], ca. 1964 (Folder 20)
  - no title (Box C102)
    - [File pocket labeled: Port. #2 letters ER -- LH], 1926-1949 (Folder 19)
      Correspondence between Hurwitz and Edwin Rolfe [a.k.a. Solomon Fishman]. Also includes a black-and-white photograph of a room from Edwin and Mary Rolfe.
  - no title (Box C104)
    - [Envelope labeled:Dialogue with a Woman Departed-- Indian words and research], ca. 1979 (Folder 3)
    - [Slides of paintings], undated (Folder 11)
      Three 35mm photographic slides of paintings, with locations indicated.
  - no title (Box C160)
    - [Box labeled: Misc. Leo Stuff], 1975; 1980-1992 (Folder 1)
      Materials include three black-and-white photographs of Hurwitz.
    - [Personal and professional correspondence, clippings], 1970; 1982; 1987; 1989 (Folder 15)
      Includes a personal letter with a color photograph.
  - no title (Box C183)
    - [Hurwitz portraits], 1969 (Folder 3)
  - no title (Box C185)
    - Miscel. from walls, ca. 1959 (Folder 7i)
  - no title (Box C192)
    - [Envelope Labeled: Early Leo Hurwitz Depression photos (slop prints)], ca. 1935 (Folder 5)
      Seven black and white Depression-era photos (approximately 4” x 6”).
    - [Folder labeled: Misc. stuff of the thirties], 1931-1937 (Folder 2d.2)
      Includes black and white photograph with text on the back in unidentifiable language.
    - [Folder labeled: Farm film], 1936; 1942 (Folder 3f)
      Includes a photograph inside Frontier Films envelope marked "picture for office" (unidentified portrait, possibly of one of the of principals of Frontier Films).
  - no title (Box C226)
    - Dance, 1944-1945 (Folder 12)
      Includes black-and-white images of Folksay being filmed, and stock black and white images to be used in the production (with notes).
  - no title (Box C227)
    - [Native Land retrospective clippings,A Harbor Anthology Outline, personal material], ca. 1930; ca. 1941; ca. 1962; 1975 (Folder 2)
      Includes a photograph of Edwin Rolfe.
    - Francesca Piatti, 1981; 1984 (Folder 18)
      Includes photograph of a tree with note by Piatti on the back.
  - no title (Box C238)
    - "They Were There", 1944 (Folder 6)
  - no title (Box C238)
    - Spotlight shows, 1945-1946 (Folder 10)
  - no title (Box OS-6)
    - [Native Land and Strange Victory scrapbook], 1941-1942; 1948 (Folder 2)
      Bound scrapbook, very fragile. Contains black-and-white photograph of Hurwitz on the set of Strange Victory.
  - no title (Box OS-7)
    - [Envelope labeled:Essay on Death-- photos regarding Kennedy assassination], ca. 1963 (Folder 1)